<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>My Blogs | QuarkQuartet</title>
    <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>My Blogs</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://quarkquartet.github.io/media/icon_hu9fe4af0edb92d3e40e98501fc4baa281_1731920_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>My Blogs</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new source of gravitation waves: particle production from bubble collision</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here I introduce a new paper that appeared on arXiv at the end of last year, from the particle physics and cosmology group in JHU, Tokyo U and DESY.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-gravitational-waves-from-particles-produced-from-bubble-collisions-in-first-order-phase-transitionshttpsarxivorgabs241217912&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[Gravitational Waves from Particles Produced from Bubble Collisions in First-Order Phase Transitions](https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_8d9545a0088bed255c963c04a1681ea3.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_787be8e6d5b350d075b1d616733fdb46.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_8d9545a0088bed255c963c04a1681ea3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;467&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gravitational Waves from Particles Produced from Bubble Collisions in First-Order Phase Transitions&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the title is pretty clear about its content, some keywords
might be difficult for people outside this specific topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important one is: first-order phase transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phase transition is a pretty widely-applied word.
Things familiar to us, such as gas-liquid transition, solid-liquid transition, are all first-order phase transitions.
The character is the existence of the specific boundary between these phases.
On the contrary, if no such a boundary exists between phases, we call it second-order phase transition.
Example could be difficult to find in daily life for second-order phase transition.
The most popular example may be the ferromagnetic phase transition that we learned in our undergrad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phase transitions also happen in the early universe.
For example, we know that particles acquire there masses from their interactions with Higgs.
But at the very early time of the universe, these masses do not exist.
Higgs, as well as other particles, is massless.
When the universe gradually cools down, masses are generated below a certain critical temperature.
This process is also a phase transition, known as the electroweak phase transition (EWPT).&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-图片来自arxivhep-ph0609145&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;图片来自arXiv:hep-ph/0609145&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_023e8b2ec0ea31f8f70fc89495c8c7c3.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_9b93979e55ce7968476f7ab7578e1d99.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_023e8b2ec0ea31f8f70fc89495c8c7c3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;556&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      图片来自arXiv:hep-ph/0609145
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no clear evidence for now whether EWPT is first-order or not.
While the Standard Model (SM) predicts a second-order PT, beyond SM physics may modify it to be first-order.
Even though EWPT finally turns out to be second-order, there is highly a chance in the early universe that a similar phase transition existing much earlier than EWPT that can be first-order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the EWPT is first-order, scenario in the above picture can happen.
Particle masses shift from 0 to a finite number, and there is a boundary between these two.
The region inside the boundary is known as the bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bubble really behaves like a physical wall. It can collide with particles surrounding it, and it can collide with another bubble wall.
And indeed, as the phase transition proceed, the bubble walls expand and really collide with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the collision between two balls in the real world can create sound wave, the bubble collisions can create gravitational waves (GW).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been answers about how the GWs are created.
In one word, it comes from the breaking of the spherical symmetry of the stress-energy tensor in the universe.
If the universe is made of homogenous things, the stress-energy tensor is apparently homogenous and spherical symmetry is kept.
However, various perturbations can break this symmetry.
Einstein&amp;rsquo;s equation tells us that GW can be produced once the stress-energy tensor is no longer spherically symmetric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we talk about these things in the context of bubbles, there are three known-types of GW sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is the bubble collision itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bubble is nothing but a shell of masses.
It carries energy.
If the bubble is not re-shaping, not colliding, but just expanding, the stress-energy tensor is still spherically symmetric, and no GW is produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when the bubbles collide with each other, the shape of shell changes.
e.g. In the above figure, bubble merges, and the shells disappear in the region where bubbles overlap.
This is not spherically symmetric, and GW can be produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.01403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gravitational waves from bubble collisions: analytic derivation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one is the sound wave after the bubble collision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early universe is not a vacuum, but rather filled by plasma.
The plasma is the most perfect fluid.
Sound wave can of course be produced by these bubbles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, if the bubbles are just expanding, the sound waves are spherically symmetric, and no GW can be produced.
The key is that the spherical symmetry in the sound wave is also broken by the bubble collision.
GW are thus source by this sound wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See：&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1608.04735&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sound shell model for acoustic gravitational wave production at a first-order phase transition in the early Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third part is MHD turbulence.
I know very rare things about it, and I&amp;rsquo;ll not review it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three sources has been known as all the sources of GW during bubble collision in the past decades.
However, the paper introduced today provides a new possible source: bubble collision can produce particles, whose energy distribution is also non-spherically-symmetric, and thus GW can be sourced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been known papers talking about particle production by bubbles.
Fast-moving bubbles are similar to colliders.
Heavy particles can be created.
The more energy the bubble shell carries, the heavier particle it can create.
This particle production mechanism could be found in a paper earlier last year.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03252v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nonthermal Heavy Dark Matter from a First-Order Phase Transition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-图片来自本文介绍的文章-httparxivorgabs241217912&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;图片来自本文介绍的文章 http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_183803752e9d3e6404bfa23a3cf56e2b.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_eeda229d781dae6b6cb03e764c58010f.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_183803752e9d3e6404bfa23a3cf56e2b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;700&#34;
               height=&#34;459&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      图片来自本文介绍的文章 &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, since spherical symmetry is already broken by the collision, the distribution of the energy carries by the particles has definitely no spherical symmetry.
GW is thus sourced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question is: is the bubble energy large enough to create this enough particles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this question, this paper gives an answer based on the widely-believed knowledge:
the wall only carries non-negligible fraction of released energy during phase transition only in vacuum or in a near-vacuum environment.
In the presence of plasma, most released energy are taken by the plasma.
This is similar to the condition under which bubble collision contribution to GW is non-negligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion of GW produced by the bubble is thus categorized in to two: Vacuum/near vacuum, or in dense plasma.
The first one typically appears in supercooling phase transitions, or in some quantum tunneling case under low temperature.
The latter one is irrelevant for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the first condition, this new source can modify the GW signal as shown in the following plot.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_4132cd3609c63ab4dc945caae127a5c6.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_e45a0646a7b29beb801ade93d99ecfff.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_4132cd3609c63ab4dc945caae127a5c6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;700&#34;
               height=&#34;490&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dashed lines are the original ones from bubble collision.
The solid lines are from the new source.
The total should be the sum of those.
We can see that the GW signal in the low-frequency region is significantly enhanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t checked the calculation in detail, but it seems good to me now.
This article should have a profound impact.
From now, papers talking about vacuum phase transitions should all utilize this result.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primordial black hole as a source of new physics detection</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to start a plan from today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll irregularly write blogs to introduce interesting paper I have noticed and read.
I&amp;rsquo;m not assuming the readers are expert, so I may write some things that look explicit/naive to some senior people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The papers may not be very new and up-to-date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;ll introduce 2 papers from the UMD theory group in the past 2 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11980&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Detecting Axion-Like Particles with Primordial Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13811&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Light in the Shadows: Primordial Black Holes Making Dark Matter Shine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/featured_hu475b9847b6d5409bd85ee852e2157b28_465076_ad866c09e12338405faa6a17755383e8.webp 400w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/featured_hu475b9847b6d5409bd85ee852e2157b28_465076_4ec0ce1a7053de486500250dbb4a147c.webp 760w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/featured_hu475b9847b6d5409bd85ee852e2157b28_465076_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/featured_hu475b9847b6d5409bd85ee852e2157b28_465076_ad866c09e12338405faa6a17755383e8.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;598&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/2_hu89cedc015026675a5e626871a7f725e3_533269_c0eda01136b19cdbd1368c7375e5c147.webp 400w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/2_hu89cedc015026675a5e626871a7f725e3_533269_51e91979b34cd37d411fd4711c6be699.webp 760w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/2_hu89cedc015026675a5e626871a7f725e3_533269_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/2_hu89cedc015026675a5e626871a7f725e3_533269_c0eda01136b19cdbd1368c7375e5c147.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can current-existing primordial black holes (PBH) help us detecting new particles? These 2 papers show a great example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first paper is very straightforward: PBH can emit particles, and thus can become a natural source of particle factory. As long as those produced particles can be detected, it&amp;rsquo;s promising for new physics discovery or exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper uses axion-like particle (ALP) as an example.
Here we assume that the ALP decays into a pair of photons.
If ALP is produced from PBH and decays into photon pair before arriving to the earth, it&amp;rsquo;s promising to be detected by future experiments like e-ASTROGRAM or AMEGO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can the Standard Model (SM) produce similar signal? Yes.
The PBH can directly radiate out photons.
However, ALP can distort the photon spectrum, and still lead to new physics discovery, shown in the following plot.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/3_huca2a2e38318615bb3460fbb6c89a2c98_138027_6529a08986dd4d3ef0198408968ce8b6.webp 400w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/3_huca2a2e38318615bb3460fbb6c89a2c98_138027_634c80b7568f59a1b379361cbe127228.webp 760w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/3_huca2a2e38318615bb3460fbb6c89a2c98_138027_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/3_huca2a2e38318615bb3460fbb6c89a2c98_138027_6529a08986dd4d3ef0198408968ce8b6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;697&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to see that ALP can change the shape of the detected photon spectrum.
After performing statistical analysis to quantify how large the deviation is between the ALP-modified spectrum and the pure SM result, we can probe ALP from the photon spectrum distortion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results shown in the next plot.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/4_huc634845a3fbf6d0262c9a25cf1d552d0_113139_1bc15cc5542317ac7a68e8fb65140c52.webp 400w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/4_huc634845a3fbf6d0262c9a25cf1d552d0_113139_10e65fad932d110557c140fa4088721b.webp 760w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/4_huc634845a3fbf6d0262c9a25cf1d552d0_113139_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/4_huc634845a3fbf6d0262c9a25cf1d552d0_113139_1bc15cc5542317ac7a68e8fb65140c52.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;721&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shaded region is the projected reach: assuming the black hole has the corresponding mass (e.g. red color means PBH haves a mass of 

$10^{15}$ g.), ALP with such a mass and coupling is projected to be discovered.
If we have such a PBH but still not discoverd, then this parameter space is excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or we can do it oppositely: if we want to probe a specific parameter space, what is the required PBH mass?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is given in the next plot: e.g. the blue curve means only PBH with parameters located in the upper region is capable of producing enough 1 MeV ALPs to be discovered.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/5_hu2837322c3a2794729296f33f46f45ed1_135685_1adb24e84d9705a77ebf55fb35e7dccd.webp 400w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/5_hu2837322c3a2794729296f33f46f45ed1_135685_566276a650920b96322ca254ddffd665.webp 760w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/5_hu2837322c3a2794729296f33f46f45ed1_135685_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/5_hu2837322c3a2794729296f33f46f45ed1_135685_1adb24e84d9705a77ebf55fb35e7dccd.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;731&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the similar way, if we go one step more, PBH can do the following for us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes dark matter annihilation nowadays is weak, and it&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to find dark matter from indirect detection (which captures the annihilation product of dark matter).
For example, asymmetric dark matter has a low current abundance of the anti-particle of the dark matter.
The dark matter cannot find is annihilation partner, and thus indirect detection is difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PBH can make it up: lack of annihilation partner? I&amp;rsquo;ll produce for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what the second paper is doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper has 2 example models. Here I would just mention one of them: the boosted anti-dark matter (BaDM). The result plot is the following:&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/6_huc4f9b906587cdbbc71e2422ff7ccc5f8_294326_341350a8e8e6fea889fd7c619605fb30.webp 400w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/6_huc4f9b906587cdbbc71e2422ff7ccc5f8_294326_83abeb09dd8dec05de1d38321fd102d3.webp 760w,
               /en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/6_huc4f9b906587cdbbc71e2422ff7ccc5f8_294326_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/PBH_newphysics_paperintro/image/6_huc4f9b906587cdbbc71e2422ff7ccc5f8_294326_341350a8e8e6fea889fd7c619605fb30.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;737&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some key points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is the detectable particle mass range determined? The answer is PBH temperature, which behaves like 

$1/M_{\rm PBH}$. A lighter PBH leads to a higher temperature, making it easier to radiate new particles. That&amp;rsquo;s why the parameter to the upper-&amp;rsquo;left&amp;rsquo; region of the curve in the above plot is capable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Too light PBH evaporate too early and cannot survive until today, so there should be a lower limit on the PBH mass. That means we cannot detect particles with arbitrarily high mass.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the advantage of PBH versus accelerators? The PBH produces particles with gravitational effects rather than particle couplings. So BSM particles can be strongly produced even if the coupling is weak. Producing a weakly-coupled particles, on the contrary, is difficult in accelerators.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, I love the introduction of the second paper!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A General Introduction to the Strong CP Problem</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/strongCP/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/strongCP/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written for people not familiar with this topic. Experts may find it trivial.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;details class=&#34;toc-inpage d-print-none  &#34; open&gt;
  &lt;summary class=&#34;font-weight-bold&#34;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#a-description-for-the-strong-cp-problem&#34;&gt;A Description for the Strong CP problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#parity-solution&#34;&gt;Parity solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#axion-solution&#34;&gt;Axion solution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-description-for-the-strong-cp-problem&#34;&gt;A Description for the Strong CP problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been a long time since we found that the Standard Model (SM) is a &lt;strong&gt;chiral&lt;/strong&gt; theory, i.e. left and right-handed particles have different properties.
Though it could be a natural, or simple, feeling, to claim that a beautiful model should be left-right symmetric, it does not seem cautious to impose this symmetry when we consider beyond Standard Model (BSM) physics until we find some really solid reason.
Fortunately, there is a problem, known as the &lt;em&gt;strong CP problem&lt;/em&gt;, that can be solved eligantly under the left-right symmetry, or known in a more professional phrase, &lt;em&gt;parity symmetry&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is strong CP problem, and how parity symmetry can solve it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you have heard about the neutron electric dipole moment (EDM). What can the dipole moment be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A naive calculation from classical physics is straightforward: the neutron contains one up-quark and two down-quarks. One can easily build a coordiante system and label the angle 

$\theta$ in a way shown in the following picture. Apparently the dipole moment is



$$
\frac{d_n}{e} \simeq 10^{-13} \sqrt{1-\cos \theta}~\mathrm{cm}
$$
&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-classical-description-for-the-neutron-edm-and-the-strong-cp-phase-taken-from-anson-hooks-lecture-notehttpsinspirehepnetliterature1707528&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A classical description for the neutron EDM and the strong CP phase. Taken from [Anson Hook&amp;#39;s lecture note](https://inspirehep.net/literature/1707528).&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/strongCP/featured_hub1761e16c2ea464147ed26ff16434e3f_61349_d932542e4e8bc34c705ed0a4ab980e0c.webp 400w,
               /en/post/strongCP/featured_hub1761e16c2ea464147ed26ff16434e3f_61349_0ad9f56853955f510d91e1c6902f26d3.webp 760w,
               /en/post/strongCP/featured_hub1761e16c2ea464147ed26ff16434e3f_61349_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/strongCP/featured_hub1761e16c2ea464147ed26ff16434e3f_61349_d932542e4e8bc34c705ed0a4ab980e0c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;50%&#34;
               height=&#34;556&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      A classical description for the neutron EDM and the strong CP phase. Taken from &lt;a href=&#34;https://inspirehep.net/literature/1707528&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anson Hook&amp;rsquo;s lecture note&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is no force to make the angle 

$\theta$ some fixed value, we would expect this angle is randomly distributed, and thus the neutron EDM. However, current experiment has shown this number to be always close to zero: we never observe any single neutron with an EDM larger than 

$10^{-26}e~\rm cm$!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This immediately implies the vanishing of the 

$\theta$ term. But why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The vanishing of this 

$\theta$ is called the &lt;em&gt;strong CP problem&lt;/em&gt;. Strictly speaking, strong CP problem is not a solid problem. You can just accept it and claim it as a coincidence. But, perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s a long-standing pursue of particle physics community, it&amp;rsquo;s just difficult for us to accept such a unnaturally small parameter in a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can&amp;rsquo;t accept it and must turn to solid problems like dark matter, emmmmmm, there is no objection. And as far as I know, the number of people who believe &amp;ldquo;strong CP problem is a problem&amp;rdquo; is as much as those who does not believe so. Just take it easy and think about it in a way you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may wonder are there any quantum-level description of the above stuff. Yes. In SM, we can chirally rotate the quark fields like 

$\psi \rightarrow \psi e^{i \gamma_5 \theta_s}$, and the Lagrangian acquires an extra term (if you are not familiar with this, you can refer to Chapter 29 and 30 of Matthew Schwartz&amp;rsquo;s textbook for quantum field theory)



$$
\mathcal{L} \rightarrow \mathcal{L} + \theta_s\frac{g_s^2}{32\pi^2} G_{\mu \nu} \tilde{G}^{\mu \nu},
$$

where the 

$G$ field is the gluon field.
Actually, since the fermion fields are not observable and can be written in any basis, the above term is generally existing and must be included in the Lagrangian.
Rotating the quark field can shift the angle 

$\theta_s$ into 

$\arg (Y_u Y_d)$, where 

$Y_{u,d}$ is the Yukawa matrix.
The difference, on the other hand, 

$\bar{\theta} \equiv \theta_s -\arg (Y_u Y_d) $, will not be changed and thus is physical!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computation shows that this angle is indeed proportional to the neutron EDM



$$
\frac{d_n}{e} \simeq 5 \times 10^{-16} \bar{\theta}~\mathrm{cm}.
$$

So the smallness of this 

$\bar{\theta}$ is the strong CP problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;parity-solution&#34;&gt;Parity solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can immediately think about it in this way: there must be some rules that forces the quarks to be aligned along a straight line! One possibility is that the neutron must be left-right symmetric, or parity-symmetric. And thus strong CP problem is solved.
The parity symmetry at the quantum level can be described as



$$
SU(2)_L \leftrightarrow SU(2)_R, Q \leftrightarrow \bar{Q}, L \leftrightarrow \bar{L}, H_L \leftrightarrow H_R.
$$

Here we use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://inspirehep.net/literature/804666&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;two-component Weyl notation for fermions&lt;/a&gt;. 

$Q$ and 

$L$ are quarks and leptons, respectively. Right-handed fermions are doublets under 

$SU(2)_R$. You can easily prove that this makes 

$\bar{\theta}$ vanishes at tree level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This solution is called the &lt;em&gt;parity solution&lt;/em&gt; to the strong CP problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;axion-solution&#34;&gt;Axion solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to think about this problem is: maybe there is an &amp;ldquo;axis&amp;rdquo; where the quarks are forced to be aligned along?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emmmm yeah that&amp;rsquo;s possible. At quantum level, we say there is a new particle whose vacuum expectation value (vev) makes the neutron EDM to be 0. This particle is called &lt;em&gt;QCD axion&lt;/em&gt;.
The Lagrangian is



$$
\mathcal{L} = \frac{a}{f_a} \frac{g_s}{32\pi^2} G_{\mu \nu} \tilde{G}^{\mu \nu} + \frac{1}{2} \partial_\mu a \partial^\mu a
$$
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The axion vev is acquired when 

$\langle a \rangle /f_a = - \theta_s$. This cancels the anomaly term and thus the strong CP problem is solved. For the details of the potential of 

$\theta_s$ term and axion, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://inspirehep.net/literature/1707528&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anson Hook&amp;rsquo;s lecture note&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lagrangian itself is not a UV-complete theory. The UV model can be various, but in common, axion is the angular degree of freedom of some complex scalar 

$P$. The potential of 

$P$ at UV has a 

$U(1)$ rotational symmetry called Peccei-Quinn symmetry. The radial mode of the field 

$P$ acquires a vev that breaks the PQ symmetry, and thus axion becomes the Nambu-Goldstone boson of 

$U(1)_{\rm PQ}$. 

$f_a$ is the symmetry breaking scale, also the radius of the axion rotation. We call it &lt;em&gt;axion decay constant&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;QCD axion is also a good dark matter candidate. And further, &lt;a href=&#34;https://inspirehep.net/literature/1757727&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a recent idea&lt;/a&gt; proposes to utilize the initial axion rotation to generate the baryon asymmetry of the universe. This new mechanism, similar to the famous Affleck-Dine baryogenesis with axion playing the role of the scalar, is named as &lt;em&gt;axiogenesis&lt;/em&gt;. Axion rotation and axiogenesis is one of the interesting and promising direction in the recent particle physics community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
