<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | QuarkQuartet</title>
    <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/tag/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://quarkquartet.github.io/tag/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://quarkquartet.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/tag/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Featured Projects</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are the current projects I&amp;rsquo;m working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;electroweak-or-electroweak-like-phase-transition-and-baryogenesis&#34;&gt;Electroweak or electroweak-like phase transition, and baryogenesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is well-known that our universe is dominated by matter instead of anti-matter, whose asymmetry remains unsolved. One promising solution to this puzzle is called &amp;ldquo;electroweak baryogenesis&amp;rdquo;. This type of mechanisms requires the electroweak phase transition (the transition of the Higgs field from the symmetric phase to the spontaneously broken phase) to be strong 1st order, which is not realized in the minimal Standard Model (SM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possible extensions on the SM to enhance the electroweak phase transition, or searching for a more promising electroweak-like phase transition at a higher energy scale has been appealing in the recent years. Details of thermodynamics, especially the computation of the thermal effective potential, on the other hand, is still tricky. I study both on model building and searches for thermodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;axion-rotation-and-axiogenesis&#34;&gt;Axion rotation and axiogenesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axion has been proposed for many years, aiming at solving the strong CP problem. It&amp;rsquo;s also a good dark matter candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, it&amp;rsquo;s been proposed that axion field can be rotating in the early universe, leading to a promising new mechanism to explain the matter-antimatter asymmetry, called &amp;ldquo;axiogenesis&amp;rdquo;. This mechanism cannot predict correct number of dark matter density and baryon asymmetry consistently in the minimal standard model. However, it&amp;rsquo;s promising to make it consistent in SM extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More interesting cosmological signals can be predicted from scalar rotations, e.g. gravitational waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I study possible extensions to improve axiogenesis and possible signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;parity-solutions-to-the-strong-cp-problem&#34;&gt;Parity solutions to the strong CP problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smallness CP-violating phase in the strong interaction has been a puzzle, and building up a parity-symmetric theory has been a well-known proposal to bring up an elegant solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecting a parity symmetric theory with baryogenesis problem and dark matter candidate is super interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;searching-for-long-lived-dark-sector-mediator-in-new-experiments&#34;&gt;Searching for long-lived dark sector mediator in new experiments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dark matter is another famous unsolved puzzle in particle physics. It may be part of an unknown &amp;ldquo;dark sector&amp;rdquo; that interacts with the SM particles only via a &amp;ldquo;mediator&amp;rdquo;. Searching for this type of mediator is thus strongly motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some light and weakly interacting mediators are particularly interesting for their potential to solve the muon $g-2$ puzzle. Those particles are typically long-lived, and gives specific experimental signatures such as displaced vertex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These particles can be searched by various types of experiments. And searches for the &amp;ldquo;mediator&amp;rdquo; can also inspire searches for other light neutral particles, such as axions or ALPs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I study on possible new searches on this type of long-lived mediators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
