<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Electroweak Phase Transition | QuarkQuartet</title>
    <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/tag/Electroweak-Phase-Transition/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/tag/Electroweak-Phase-Transition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Electroweak Phase Transition</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://quarkquartet.github.io/media/icon_hu9fe4af0edb92d3e40e98501fc4baa281_1731920_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Electroweak Phase Transition</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/tag/Electroweak-Phase-Transition/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Discriminant Power of Bubble Wall Velocities: Gravitational Waves and Electroweak Baryogenesis</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/Wall_velocity_LTE/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/Wall_velocity_LTE/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new source of gravitation waves: particle production from bubble collision</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here I introduce a new paper that appeared on arXiv at the end of last year, from the particle physics and cosmology group in JHU, Tokyo U and DESY.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-gravitational-waves-from-particles-produced-from-bubble-collisions-in-first-order-phase-transitionshttpsarxivorgabs241217912&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;[Gravitational Waves from Particles Produced from Bubble Collisions in First-Order Phase Transitions](https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912)&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_8d9545a0088bed255c963c04a1681ea3.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_787be8e6d5b350d075b1d616733fdb46.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/1_hube1f9fffbee0f063d48d0c6f28b87625_316478_8d9545a0088bed255c963c04a1681ea3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;467&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gravitational Waves from Particles Produced from Bubble Collisions in First-Order Phase Transitions&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the title is pretty clear about its content, some keywords
might be difficult for people outside this specific topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important one is: first-order phase transition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phase transition is a pretty widely-applied word.
Things familiar to us, such as gas-liquid transition, solid-liquid transition, are all first-order phase transitions.
The character is the existence of the specific boundary between these phases.
On the contrary, if no such a boundary exists between phases, we call it second-order phase transition.
Example could be difficult to find in daily life for second-order phase transition.
The most popular example may be the ferromagnetic phase transition that we learned in our undergrad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phase transitions also happen in the early universe.
For example, we know that particles acquire there masses from their interactions with Higgs.
But at the very early time of the universe, these masses do not exist.
Higgs, as well as other particles, is massless.
When the universe gradually cools down, masses are generated below a certain critical temperature.
This process is also a phase transition, known as the electroweak phase transition (EWPT).&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-图片来自arxivhep-ph0609145&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;图片来自arXiv:hep-ph/0609145&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_023e8b2ec0ea31f8f70fc89495c8c7c3.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_9b93979e55ce7968476f7ab7578e1d99.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/2_huf758ee77f1e77bd56b9fe47383fe3282_256158_023e8b2ec0ea31f8f70fc89495c8c7c3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;600&#34;
               height=&#34;556&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      图片来自arXiv:hep-ph/0609145
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no clear evidence for now whether EWPT is first-order or not.
While the Standard Model (SM) predicts a second-order PT, beyond SM physics may modify it to be first-order.
Even though EWPT finally turns out to be second-order, there is highly a chance in the early universe that a similar phase transition existing much earlier than EWPT that can be first-order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the EWPT is first-order, scenario in the above picture can happen.
Particle masses shift from 0 to a finite number, and there is a boundary between these two.
The region inside the boundary is known as the bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bubble really behaves like a physical wall. It can collide with particles surrounding it, and it can collide with another bubble wall.
And indeed, as the phase transition proceed, the bubble walls expand and really collide with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the collision between two balls in the real world can create sound wave, the bubble collisions can create gravitational waves (GW).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been answers about how the GWs are created.
In one word, it comes from the breaking of the spherical symmetry of the stress-energy tensor in the universe.
If the universe is made of homogenous things, the stress-energy tensor is apparently homogenous and spherical symmetry is kept.
However, various perturbations can break this symmetry.
Einstein&amp;rsquo;s equation tells us that GW can be produced once the stress-energy tensor is no longer spherically symmetric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we talk about these things in the context of bubbles, there are three known-types of GW sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is the bubble collision itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bubble is nothing but a shell of masses.
It carries energy.
If the bubble is not re-shaping, not colliding, but just expanding, the stress-energy tensor is still spherically symmetric, and no GW is produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when the bubbles collide with each other, the shape of shell changes.
e.g. In the above figure, bubble merges, and the shells disappear in the region where bubbles overlap.
This is not spherically symmetric, and GW can be produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1605.01403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gravitational waves from bubble collisions: analytic derivation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one is the sound wave after the bubble collision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early universe is not a vacuum, but rather filled by plasma.
The plasma is the most perfect fluid.
Sound wave can of course be produced by these bubbles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, if the bubbles are just expanding, the sound waves are spherically symmetric, and no GW can be produced.
The key is that the spherical symmetry in the sound wave is also broken by the bubble collision.
GW are thus source by this sound wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See：&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1608.04735&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sound shell model for acoustic gravitational wave production at a first-order phase transition in the early Universe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third part is MHD turbulence.
I know very rare things about it, and I&amp;rsquo;ll not review it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three sources has been known as all the sources of GW during bubble collision in the past decades.
However, the paper introduced today provides a new possible source: bubble collision can produce particles, whose energy distribution is also non-spherically-symmetric, and thus GW can be sourced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been known papers talking about particle production by bubbles.
Fast-moving bubbles are similar to colliders.
Heavy particles can be created.
The more energy the bubble shell carries, the heavier particle it can create.
This particle production mechanism could be found in a paper earlier last year.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03252v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nonthermal Heavy Dark Matter from a First-Order Phase Transition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-图片来自本文介绍的文章-httparxivorgabs241217912&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;图片来自本文介绍的文章 http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_183803752e9d3e6404bfa23a3cf56e2b.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_eeda229d781dae6b6cb03e764c58010f.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/featured_hu641bea3b0bc0c08eddb369f5e5102fe6_112726_183803752e9d3e6404bfa23a3cf56e2b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;700&#34;
               height=&#34;459&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      图片来自本文介绍的文章 &lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17912&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, since spherical symmetry is already broken by the collision, the distribution of the energy carries by the particles has definitely no spherical symmetry.
GW is thus sourced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question is: is the bubble energy large enough to create this enough particles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this question, this paper gives an answer based on the widely-believed knowledge:
the wall only carries non-negligible fraction of released energy during phase transition only in vacuum or in a near-vacuum environment.
In the presence of plasma, most released energy are taken by the plasma.
This is similar to the condition under which bubble collision contribution to GW is non-negligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion of GW produced by the bubble is thus categorized in to two: Vacuum/near vacuum, or in dense plasma.
The first one typically appears in supercooling phase transitions, or in some quantum tunneling case under low temperature.
The latter one is irrelevant for this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the first condition, this new source can modify the GW signal as shown in the following plot.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_4132cd3609c63ab4dc945caae127a5c6.webp 400w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_e45a0646a7b29beb801ade93d99ecfff.webp 760w,
               /en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/GW_particleproduction_paper/image/3_hu06a32a8826663a5649ebbcb5cfb09620_299114_4132cd3609c63ab4dc945caae127a5c6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;700&#34;
               height=&#34;490&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dashed lines are the original ones from bubble collision.
The solid lines are from the new source.
The total should be the sum of those.
We can see that the GW signal in the low-frequency region is significantly enhanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t checked the calculation in detail, but it seems good to me now.
This article should have a profound impact.
From now, papers talking about vacuum phase transitions should all utilize this result.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALP-assisted strong first-order electroweak phase transition and baryogenesis</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/ALP_EWPT/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/ALP_EWPT/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electroweak (-like) baryogenesis</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/project/EWBG/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/project/EWBG/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is known that Higgs potential is spontaneously broken in the current universe.
However, if no new physics is appearing, the symmetry would be restored at high temperature.
The transition from the restored Higgs potential symmetric phase to the broken phase during the universe cooling down is called the electroweak phase transition (EWPT).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If new physics appear, depending on the form of new physics, the phase transition may be enhanced, or on the other hand, the symmetry may not be restored at high temperature.
Both are strongly motivated for various problems, especially by the baryogenesis problem.
Specifically, in 1985, it was presented that &lt;a href=&#34;https://inspirehep.net/literature/214544&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;electroweak phase transition may provide the necessary condition for baryogenesis if it&amp;rsquo;s strongly first order&lt;/a&gt;.
This mechanism is known as electroweak baryogenesis (EWBG).
However, the phase transition is known to be a smooth crossover after Higgs mass was measured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the end of the story. People know that a simple scalar extension in the Higgs sector could enhance the phase transition so that a strongly first-order phase transition may appear.
On the other hand, if the real model of this world contains a larger gauge group and multiple electroweak-like phase transitions in the early history, this mechanism may still work at some moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, there are a few things below that worth investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;models-including-electroweak-like-phase-transition-at-high-energy-scale&#34;&gt;Models including electroweak-like phase transition at high energy scale&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have tons of models that include a gauge group symmetry breaking pattern at high energy scale. For example, the &lt;a href=&#34;../parity/index.md&#34;&gt;parity-symmetric model&lt;/a&gt; contains a phase transition 

$SU(2)_R \times U(1)_X \to U(1)_Y$.
More interesting phase transition also appears, for example, in GUT theroy, in twin-Higgs theory, and so forth.
The phase transition happens for different scalar fields, or have different interactions, or have different coupling strength, compared to the standard model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in parity-symmetric model, the running coupling, especially the running of 

$\lambda$, will make the achievement of a strong first-order phase transition much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be a very interesting direction to investigate the phase transition and phase thermal history of those models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;computation-of-phase-transition-quantities&#34;&gt;Computation of phase transition quantities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the electroweak phase transition is very technical. The prediction of baryon asymmetry is pretty controversial.
These include (but not limited to):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wall velocity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baryon number asymmetry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Phase transition strength&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a trustable method, we cannot make prediction for models.
Given the strong motivation for electroweak (-like) phase transition stated before, it could be very valuable to improve the computation of various quantities in the phase transition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parity-symmetric model</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/project/parity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/project/parity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parity is a good solution to the strong CP problem. I have written a &lt;a href=&#34;https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/post/strongCP/#a-description-for-the-strong-cp-problem&#34;&gt;post for strong CP problem and its solutions&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, we can have a gauge group of the standard parity-symmetric model 

$SU(3)_C \times SU(2)_L \times SU(2)_R \times U(1)_{B-L}$. The next step is: &lt;strong&gt;can this model provide us more solutions to other unsolved puzzles&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been working in this direction. Things included are: dark matter, baryogenesis, and neutrino masses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;baryogenesis-in-parity-symmetric-model&#34;&gt;Baryogenesis in parity-symmetric model&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baryogenesis in a parity solution to the strong CP problem</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/Parity_EWBG/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/Parity_EWBG/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Axiogenesis from $SU(2)_R$ phase transition</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/Axiogenesis_SU2R/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/Axiogenesis_SU2R/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electroweak-like baryogenesis with new chiral matter</title>
      <link>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/EWBG_chiral_matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://quarkquartet.github.io/en/publication/EWBG_chiral_matter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
